<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>pdt's Blog!</title><link href="http://blog.pdt.space/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.pdt.space/feeds/stuffs.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.pdt.space/</id><updated>2015-09-07T18:35:00+07:00</updated><entry><title>Some more thoughts from my trip back home</title><link href="http://blog.pdt.space/posts/2015/09/some-more-thoughts-from-my-trip-back-home/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-09-07T18:35:00+07:00</updated><author><name>pdt</name></author><id>tag:blog.pdt.space,2015-09-07:posts/2015/09/some-more-thoughts-from-my-trip-back-home/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned before, I was avoiding work during my visit back home.
I called it &amp;#8220;e-detox&amp;#8221;. However, I did try to make some observations on
how people use tech in their daily life. One thing to note is that
I wasn&amp;#8217;t able to travel a lot, my I did spend time in multiple cities,
all of which are big and more developed however (like Sai Gon and Da&amp;nbsp;Nang).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="people-use-smartphones-everwhere"&gt;People use smartphones everwhere&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#people-use-smartphones-everwhere" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually start my first day in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VN&lt;/span&gt; by fixing all the mobile devices in my home for
my family. I counted a grand number of 6. Take my mom for example, before I left
for college, she was technically useless. Now she was asking me how to integrate
her credit card to use Uber on her phone (more on this later). My gf, my father,
my sister and my brother in law all have one or more phones, all but one are&amp;nbsp;smartphones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From those who I interact with, all use smartphone everytime everywhere. Either for
calling me here in France via skype/viber or send texts to their relatives on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FB&lt;/span&gt;.
Most of the devices are Android, with Window Phones behind but you can spot
quite a lot of iPhones too. People still have some hope in the Nokia brand,
thus explaining the success of Microsoft/&lt;span class="caps"&gt;WP&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="mobile-plans-are-cheap"&gt;Mobile plans are cheap&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#mobile-plans-are-cheap" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find call/data plans rather cheap. You can buy, say &lt;span class="caps"&gt;3GB&lt;/span&gt; of data very easily from
billions of kiots from the streets. Otherwise you can go to any cafe and enjoy their
high-speed connection. This is expected, I never saw any cafe without a proper internet
connection. This is where people to go hangout with their friend next to a cup of coffee,
surfing the nets and for some, getting some work&amp;nbsp;done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SIM&lt;/span&gt; card is equally easy. I think I paid 10e for my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SIM&lt;/span&gt; card, with some
data credit and yet I still had some left. With that price, I could live with
the connection&amp;nbsp;instability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the people I know use prepaid plan and never on contract, very different from&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="fb-is-king"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FB&lt;/span&gt; is king&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#fb-is-king" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone&amp;#8217;s on fb, despite all the efforts from the goverment.
There exist some competition from local services that are quite
decent like Yalo (that I don&amp;#8217;t use due to privacy concerns)
and Viber/Skype (for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OTT&lt;/span&gt; calling/&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SMS&lt;/span&gt;). I don&amp;#8217;t think a lot of people use
Twitter, yet forums are still very&amp;nbsp;popular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="e-commerce-e-payment"&gt;E-commerce / e-payment&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#e-commerce-e-payment" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to always have some cash with you. More and more merchandises accept
cards but far from ubiquitous and the fees are quite excessive. I successfully
convinced my mom to go to the bank to get a debit card with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VISA&lt;/span&gt; so see can
use &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UBER&lt;/span&gt; instead of taxis. Yeah, she hated taxis that much since getting
an account/card is not an easy task (I&amp;#8217;ll write about my own expereine in the future).
Then right after that, probably one day or twos, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UBER&lt;/span&gt; announced they give it up
and allowed cash for transactions.&amp;nbsp;Well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But of course, she could use the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VISA&lt;/span&gt; for tons other things. E-commerce is still
in its very first step of development but has a very bright future. Since cash
rules, people opt for paying by cash on delivery. I find it rather uncomfortable
but many really dont trust&amp;nbsp;e-payment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="end"&gt;End&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#end" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also had a chance to talk to my friend who are very involved in the tech scene in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VN&lt;/span&gt;.
They&amp;#8217;re all very optimistic about the future. Smartphones with connection easy to get,
people being high tech savvy and their very own habits, tons of things waiting
for being disrupted; all of those shouting&amp;nbsp;potential. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="tech"></category><category term="dev"></category><category term="stuffs"></category></entry><entry><title>Random thoughts after my trip back to home</title><link href="http://blog.pdt.space/posts/2015/08/random-thoughts-after-my-trip-back-to-home/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-08-30T21:44:00+07:00</updated><author><name>pdt</name></author><id>tag:blog.pdt.space,2015-08-30:posts/2015/08/random-thoughts-after-my-trip-back-to-home/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;The longer one hesitates before the door the stranger one becomes&amp;#8221;.
Several weeks ago, after nearly one year, I decided enough is enough and went to buy the plane&amp;nbsp;ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve always thought that home is not fixed to a place but rather where your loved ones are.
Well, in this case my long-time girl friend and all of my family are currently back in my home&amp;nbsp;country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a tremendous time there, letting your guard down being around those you care most about.
Not to mention food: I could eat properly again. Mom, if you&amp;#8217;re reading this (I highly doubt),
I really miss your cooking. I also had a chance to catch up with my old friends, see what&amp;#8217;re they up to
(Ok, i lied, I can do that on facebook too), made some new amazing friends and heard some great stories
to tell people here in&amp;nbsp;France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my going flight, I sat next to this young German dude called Tim. Tim is a police office traveling with
another country fellow whose name I did not catch. Anyway, I learned a great deal about his line of work in Germany
after our conversations which lasted hours. As Tim &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; his friend traveled with a &amp;#8220;surprise me&amp;#8221; mindset they didn&amp;#8217;t plan
any thing, at all. So I tried to give him some suggestions and recommendations, you know like what bar to hit and how
to go around, things like that. I also convinced him to go check-out a striking bay called &amp;#8220;Ha Long&amp;#8221;, a very famous tourist
destination. The thing is I hadn&amp;#8217;t check the news before that as there were heavy flooding and waste pollution
from surrounding coal mines that caused around 20 deaths! I tried to warn him by email but I have yet to receive his reply, so i&amp;#8217;m a bit&amp;nbsp;worried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, most of the time I tried not to work. It&amp;#8217;s a bit weird since I tend to use my laptop a lot.
If not in the office, I would be reading something or learning a new stuff or just messing around out of curiosity.
I would also from time to time help out my girl friend with her work related to programming, mostly &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VBA&lt;/span&gt; stuffs.
So yeah, it&amp;#8217;s probably the longest period of time I don&amp;#8217;t code over the last few&amp;nbsp;years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as usual, I did a ton of technical support meaning cleaning home &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt;, upgrading the machines, installing AdBlocks,
I even config a new &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; for my brother in law&amp;#8217;s company &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt;. At least, it&amp;#8217;s not via TeamViewer,
I told to myself so it&amp;#8217;s (probably) all&amp;nbsp;good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time flies like an arrow, the vacation&amp;#8217;s finally over before I even knew it. I really wished I could stay a bit longer
so that I could spend more time with my girl friend. Let my tell you one more time: long distance relationship sucks!
But I guess &amp;#8220;how lucky I am to have something that makes saying goodbye so hard&amp;#8221;, so, thanks for making it a great trip everybody!
I miss you all (you too Tim, if you&amp;#8217;re still&amp;nbsp;alive)&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="stuffs"></category></entry></feed>